<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://yangchenyun.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yangchenyun.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-01-02T21:55:26+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://yangchenyun.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Annual Review 2011]]></title>
    <link href="http://yangchenyun.github.com/2011/12/annual-review/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-31T23:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://yangchenyun.github.com/2011/12/annual-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="a-successful-turning-of-life">A Successful Turning of Life</h2>

<p>2011 is crucial to me. Straying away from my Economics background, I started learning web design and development from scratch and ended up with a result better than my expectation.</p>

<h3 id="highlights">Highlights</h3>

<p>On March 14th, I made a <a href="http://ge.tt/3XTYjJg?" title="Presentation about what hinders adult from learning" target="_blank">presentation</a> at Barcamp Shanghai talking about what hinders adult learning and I met Peter and later the whole TEDxFSS team.</p>

<p>On May 15th, I designed and deployed <a href="http://tedxfivestarsquare.com" target="_blank">the site of TEDxFiveStarSquare</a> and later designed the banner, poster and screen for the event. This solidates my confidence to deliver design and development work.</p>

<p>On June 7th, I started the <a href="http://ele.me/napos.php" title="Link to Eleme Napos" target="_blank">Napos</a> project at <a href="http://ele.me/at/entry/1" target="_blank">Eleme</a> and later I joined the team and took charge of UI design and frontend development.</p>

<p>On August 21th, I made a <a href="http://yangchenyun.github.com/2011/08/tedxyouth-wesklake-speech/" target="_blank">speech</a> on TEDxYouth Westlake about making a change in your life at TEDxYouth West-lake.</p>

<h3 id="excerpt-of-2011">Excerpt of 2011</h3>

<p><img src="http://yangchenyun.github.com/images/tedxfss_logo.png" alt="TEDxFiveStarSquare Logo" class="left" />
  I expected one year preparation before I could deliver qualified projects. But the first website was accomplished after five months of learning. I built <a href="http://tedxfivestarsquare.com" target="_blank">the website of TEDxFiveStarSquare(TEDxFSS)</a> and later contributed to the design of the whole event. With the help of a great team, we pull off the only one <a href="http://www.sxn.me/gallery/#/Gallery/TEDx%20FiveStarSquare%202011%20-%20May%2015%202011" title="TEDxFSS Event" target="_blank">TEDx Event</a> in Shanghai.</p>

<p>After that, I joined in a start-up company and created a <a href="http://ele.me/napos.php" title="Link to Eleme Napos" target="_blank">webapp</a> for restaurants and contributed to the <a href="http://ele.me/at/entry/1" target="_blank">new website</a> redesign and later led the frontend development.</p>

<p>Thanks to the people I worked with, I also have fallen in love with Unix and learned to setup various backend service. A summary on technology learned will cover this geeky issue.</p>

<p>The progress is mostly due to the <a href="http://yangchenyun.github.com/2011/12/annual-review/#personal-management-system" title="section of personal management system">personal management system</a> I have developed to manage my times and goals. In 2011, I <strong>recorded 7.58 hours</strong> and worked with focus <strong>4.18 hours everyday</strong>.</p>

<p>However in other aspects, things haven’t worked out as expected. Due to my work English learning have been paused in the second half year and travel plan to Southern Asia was canceled. Besides I have been suffering from anxieties from time to time and getting up early still eludes me.</p>

<p>From the ups and downs of 2011, I learned a lot <a href="http://yangchenyun.github.com/2011/12/lesson-learned/" title="Lesson I have learned" target="_blank">lessons</a> and I am thinking about moving forward.</p>

<h2 id="a-more-close-look-at-2011">A More Close Look at 2011</h2>

<h3 id="english-writing">English Writing</h3>
<p>The biggest achievement for English study is that I have developed a memorizing system with <a href="http://www.supermemo.com/english/princip.htm" title="Supermemo methods" target="_blank">Supermemo</a> methodology for learning. I collected sentences and words from my reading and quoted the detailed explanation in that context from dictionaries. Later this collection was transformed into Supermemo items (with the format of xml) through a script. The Supermemo software then took care of the repetition plans.</p>

<p>Through out the year, I have remembered <strong>2151</strong> sentences, <strong>1412</strong> Nouns, <strong>441</strong> oral phrases and <strong>2477</strong> words spelling.</p>

<p>The repetition plans are calculated according to the supermemo algorithm which makes sure I will remember what I have learned. The learning effort becomes accumulative.</p>

<p>Although working out well, the performance still fell short of the goals as I had paused learning new words in the 2nd half year due to my work. A initial habit breaking in June finally led to a permanent stop. In November, I had more than 3000 drills need to be caught up with.</p>

<p>For the same reason, I also missed the goals for English reading and writing.</p>

<p>I planned to write 15 publishable articles (20,000 words) but I only ended up in only <a href="http://ge.tt/3XTYjJg?" title="Presentation about what hinders adult from learning" target="_blank">one</a> and some drafts. I also missed the goal to finish 10 non-tech English books. There were about ten books I have opened this year but I didn’t finish all of them.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Hermann Hesse - Siddhartha, listened several times with audio version.</li>
  <li>Rilke - Letters To A Young Poet, read through once.</li>
  <li>Ernest Hemingway - The Old Man and the Sea, read through several times and recited the first 20% of the book.</li>
  <li>Carson McCullers - The Heart is a Lonely Hunter, finished Part one</li>
  <li>Malcolm Gladwell - Outliers -The Story Of Success, listened the audiobook.</li>
  <li>Malcolm Gladwell - Blink, listened with the audiobook.</li>
  <li>Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi - Flow, read through once</li>
  <li>Anne Lamott - Bird by Bird, read 50% of all chapters</li>
</ul>

<p>The biggest achievement is that I have accustomized myself to reading electronic books. I built myself an search-able library and I also customize the <a href="http://www.tracker-software.com/product/pdf-xchange-viewer" title="PDF-XChange Viewer" target="_blank">great PDF reader</a> with an highlight system to mark while reading. With the notes and comments, I could archive the same reading experience as reading a paper book while gain the ability to search with convenience.</p>

<h3 id="web-design-and-computer-science">Web Design and Computer Science</h3>
<p>I wanted myself to be a “qualified web designer” in the beginning of the year and thanks to my full-time work in the second half year I have exceeded this goal by all means.</p>

<p>I have acquired all the core skills I planned to master - <code>HTML5</code>, <code>CSS</code>, <code>javaScript</code> and created five sites. Besides, I also have switched my workspace to Unix (FreeBSD in specific), learned to setup servers (HTTP, SSH etc.), learned basic <code>Ruby</code> scripting and also contributed <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/users/966437/steven-yang" title="Stackoverflow Profile" target="_blank">a little back to the community</a>.</p>

<p>Beyond the details of various technology, I began to form a big picture about the whole “web stack” - how a browser renders to a user based on HTTP response processed by the server. This guide map now provides me a clear clue about what I need to learn in the future.</p>

<p>The part that fell short is the financial income. I began to get incomes in June but I didn’t reach my goals for saving. The reason is that I compromised my salary for expected options. As I left the team, those promise won’t be cashed in. I was also quite inactive on the business side. I didn’t make any effort to negotiate my incomes or look for contract projects.</p>

<h3 id="travel">Travel</h3>
<p>Although I have processed material and booked three tickets to Malaysia, Indonesia and Thailand, I canceled the itinerary because of work in the second half year.</p>

<p>I set travel the highest priority in the planning, but along the time, I found becoming a good developer and designer motivates me much more than travel. Near the end of year <a href="http://www.tudou.com/programs/view/tr48fLU-dNA/" title="Nancy's Speech" target="_blank">Nancy from ScentLibrary</a> also asked me “Why are you travel?”. It makes me powder my motivation underneath - exploration is just a process not a goal, so what is my ultimate goal of living?</p>

<p>This stunning question provides a clue I need to follow.</p>

<h3 id="physical-training-and-habit">Physical Training and Habit</h3>

<h4 id="personal-management-system">Personal Management System</h4>
<p>The corner stone for all my growth is the time management system I invented by combining the methods of GTD, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pomodoro_Technique" title="Pomodoro Methods" target="_blank">Pomodoro</a> and <a href="http://book.douban.com/subject/1115353/" title="Lyubishchev's Methods" target="_blank">Lyubishchev</a>. I used GTD method to setup top-down goals and break them down to single tasks. Everyday I cleared my task stack one by one. At last, I recorded and audited my time spending to detect spaces for improvement. I edited the sheet created by <a href="chrisguillebeau.com/3x5/" title="aonc site" target="_blank">Chris@ANOC</a> and I invented my own sheet for weekly and daily planning. You could find the whole toolkit <a href="http://ge.tt/9Rf7BoB?c" title="personal management toolkit" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<p>I also did some improvement to this system while I am using it:</p>

<ul>
  <li>I add the feature-week and feature-day to ramp up energy for starting some new projects;</li>
  <li>I separates the hours of working and learning;</li>
  <li>I wrote down everyday tasks in the beginning of the week;</li>
  <li>I would use several pomodoros in a row to handle big tasks;</li>
  <li>I also record normal time spendings.</li>
</ul>

<p>The lesson learned with this system is:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Always</strong> start your week with a plan.
When you postponed the planning, I have whiled away my time in 78 days.</li>
  <li>Plan loosely, work hardly.
In the first several weeks, I packed too much tasks into a week. It overwhelmingly exceeded my capacity and resulted in anxiety and frustration.</li>
  <li>Leave flexible time with planning.
I find there are always some inevitable sporadic events I need to handle.</li>
  <li>Always motivate yourself.
I recorded 1742 hours in the first 30 weeks and only recorded 433 in the later 22. This happens because when I am at work, I cut the time for inspiration. This huge productivity decline is caused by lack of motivation.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="physical-training-and-health">Physical Training and Health</h4>
<p>I did a bad job in health and training. From January to June, I would swim twice every week and from March I would do 100 push-ups everyday. However the exercise time was still less than the 30 min everyday. This situation was worse in the second half year.</p>

<p>As a result, I began to suffer from aches at shoulder and low backbone. In the end of the year, the pain could even last the whole day and make sitting an discomfortable position.</p>

<p>Another setback in health is my biological clock. The habit of getting up early still eluded me. I was still quite exciting after midnight and I used to work later than 12:00pm since May. The situation got worse when I went to work where I slept later than 2:00am in average. With the shift in sleeping hours, I also have shifted the time I get up - usually 8 hours after I went to bed.</p>

<p>This shift in sleeping hours dispairs my sleeping quality and I felt a decline in endurance and time of focus when I am working.</p>

<p>[link_to_move_forward]</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson Learned]]></title>
    <link href="http://yangchenyun.github.com/2011/12/lesson-learned/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-31T21:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://yangchenyun.github.com/2011/12/lesson-learned</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="lesson-1-know-how-to-sustain-yourself">Lesson 1: Know How to Sustain Yourself</h2>

<p>Making decision is hard, but stick with it is much harder. when I was struggling with self-doubt and fear, I developed two ways to sustain myself: <strong>feed your motivation</strong>(with <a href="http://quote.yangchenyun.com" title="My Quotes" target="_blank">Qotto</a>) and <strong>always take actions</strong>.</p>

<h3 id="the-full-story">The Full Story</h3>
<p>After the first thrilling week after I dived into computer science, things turned out to be much more difficult than I thought before. It’s as if without preparation I walked into a Arabic village with a map full of mystical symbols which seems to contain the biggest secret of the city. I started with the simpliest ones, tried to understand it through searching and asking.</p>

<p>After I have acquired the basic knowledge, I soon realized that there are more areas I need to explore, the map I had is just the entrance of a much bigger world. From times to times, I received news about this bigger world. The more news I heart about it, the eager I wanted to see it, the more frustrating I became - because it is far away from where I am.</p>

<p>Besides the frustrating endless journey, loneliness is another threat. Because I have no experience in this fields, I constantly doubt myself - Am I choose the right way? Am I walking too slowly or too fast? How long will it take to reach the next station? Without an companion, the only effort to comfort myself is to ignore them.</p>

<p>The excitement and thrilling hope soon subsided. Fear and doubt began to accumulate and finally dominated myself. I was worn out. There comes the time when I found myself ulterly useless. I was 24 and I cannot even feed myself. I tried to carve out in a new field but didn’t know whether I am on the right track. Not to mention the endless road I am walking on.
  Is it time to give up?</p>

<p><img src="http://yangchenyun.github.com/images/yelling.jpg" alt="My yelling self" class="right" />
  I had no answer to that question. All I know is that I have chosen a novel fields to explore and if I gave up and started to explore I had to experience the same frustration. If this <strong>pattern</strong> couldn’t be overcome, I will go nowhere further than where I am. I had to sustain myself and keep on walking.</p>

<p>To deal with the fear and doubt, I developed the <a href="http://quote.yangchenyun.com" title="My Quotes" target="_blank">Qotto</a> to provide inspiration for me. I set it as my default browser page and feed motivation throughout the day.</p>

<p>Whenever I feel overwhelmed by self-doubt, I force myself to do something - begin reading one or two pages, write several lines of code or write down the fear and doubt.The actions I took always provide me some positive feedback, this feedback makes me feel better.</p>

<h2 id="lesson-2-dont-avoid-the-boring-work">Lesson 2: Don’t avoid the boring work</h2>

<p>After working on the some personal projects and later in a start-up company, I learned getting the boring things done is necessary to deliver great work.</p>

<p>Every task has their 20% exciting and 80% boring part but it is <strong>usually the 80% boring part determines the quality of the work</strong>. It applies to every type of work.</p>

<p>When I was writing <a href="http://ge.tt/3XTYjJg" title="Presentation about what hinders adult from learning" target="_blank">the article</a>, there are dull process such as seeking for the right words to express my idea or correct mistakes in spelling, grammar or word usage. The same applies to design. Andy and Dai (two co-workers at ele.me) used more than 60 days to just adjust the color, icons, button shapes, border lines and other details on the iOS app they are developing. Coding is no exception. When start from scratch, it’s not about writing the elegant solution right away, it’s ususlly about writing a piece of code, testing, editing former code, testing and moving on. After the first workable solution, you will refactor the code every day.</p>

<p>Those boring parts are necessary because they are in the process which guarantees the quality of output. Without word refinement and spell checking, I couldn’t deliver it out; without improvement on details, current ele.me iOS app won’t be stunning elegant; without continuous refactoring there won’t be beautiful code.</p>

<p>It is the boring parts which separates professionals and amateurs.</p>

<h2 id="lesson-3-guard-against-distraction">Lesson 3: Guard Against Distraction</h2>
<p>Along the year, I recorded 130 new ideas (big or small) and took actions on 43 ones. Some are improvement on what I had been doing and some are sporadic interest in one field. The list covers:</p>

<pre><code>* Learning Drovak Keyboard
* Attend 54 Frequent miles program
* Recite &lt;the old man and sea&gt;
* Dig into Wordpress
* Learning Django
* Worked on several side projects
</code></pre>

<p>All of these projects doesn’t sustain longer than one month. Thus the time spent is wasted. This is the <strong>cost of distraction</strong>. What if I turned down all of them but focus my time on one project? At least I would have another output which might be useful.</p>

<p>It takes time to pull even single one idea off, so I need to guard myself against distraction. I will learn to detect distractions and then prevent yourself from taking actions on them.</p>

<p>To detect distractions, the <strong>minimal viable rules</strong> help a lot. I will check the idea againt the question ‘is it necessary to accomplish my goal?’. If the answer is not an absolutely ‘yes’, it is an distraction.</p>

<p>To prevent taking action, I will ask another question against it - ‘will you do it one month later? six month later? one year later?’ It the answer is no, I won’t start it because I cannot sustain myself until I finished it.</p>

<h2 id="lesson-4-slow-slow-slow">Lesson 4: Slow, Slow, Slow</h2>

<h2 id="lesson-5-be-careful-about-opportunity">Lesson 5: Be careful about ‘Opportunity’</h2>
<p>[Lessons learned from ele.me]</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Talk@TEDxYouth Westlake]]></title>
    <link href="http://yangchenyun.github.com/2011/08/tedxyouth-wesklake-speech/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-21T00:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://yangchenyun.github.com/2011/08/tedxyouth-wesklake-speech</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-holds-us-back-from-changes">What Holds Us Back from Changes</h2>

<p><img src="http://yangchenyun.github.com/images/tedxwl_logo.png" alt="TEDxFiveStarSquare Logo" class="right" />
This is the a talk I made at <a href="http://www.ted.com/tedx/events/3030" title="TEDxYouth Details">TEDxYouth WeskLake</a> on August 21th 2011.</p>

<p>I talked about lessons learned from my experience to change career path from Economics background to web designer and developer in 301 days.</p>

<embed class="" src="http://www.tudou.com/v/juhnvWn997s/v.swf" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" wmode="opaque" width="480" height="360" />

<div style="width:480px; margin:0 auto;" id="__ss_10760600"><object id="__sse10760600" width="480" height="404"><param name="movie" value="http://static.slidesharecdn.com/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=whatholdsusbackfromchanges-120102035627-phpapp01&amp;stripped_title=what-holds-us-back-from-changes&amp;userName=yangchenyun" /><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" /><param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always" /><param name="wmode" value="transparent" /><embed name="__sse10760600" src="http://static.slidesharecdn.com/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=whatholdsusbackfromchanges-120102035627-phpapp01&amp;stripped_title=what-holds-us-back-from-changes&amp;userName=yangchenyun" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" wmode="transparent" width="480" height="404" /></object></div>

<p>The related files could be found <a href="http://ge.tt/97rT6pB" title="Presentation Files of my TEDxYouth Talk">here</a>.</p>

<p>Thanks for all the lovely organizers to pull this event off.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
