<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: study | Steven Yang's Blog | 杨晨昀]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.yangchenyun.com/blog/categories/study/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.yangchenyun.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-18T21:20:28+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.yangchenyun.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Steven Yang]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Finished the DBClass from Stanford with Full Score]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.yangchenyun.com/2013/03/how-i-finished-the-dbclass-from-stanford-with-full-score/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-24T20:44:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.yangchenyun.com/2013/03/how-i-finished-the-dbclass-from-stanford-with-full-score</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#the-summary-of-material">The Summary of Material</a></li>
  <li><a href="#how-i-approach-the-course-differently">How I Approach the Course Differently</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#more-reading-and-practice">More Reading and Practice</a></li>
      <li><a href="#tune-the-tools">Tune the Tools</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#whats-next">What’s next?</a></li>
</ul>

<p>For the past ten weeks, I’ve been working the <a href="https://class2go.stanford.edu/db/Winter2013">DBClass</a> offered by Standord. With 40 hours’ study I achieved <a href="/assets/download/db-statement.pdf">distinguished statement with full score</a> on all exercises and both exams. </p>

<p>In this course, I’ve acquired a solid knowledge about the algebra used behind the SQL language, learned advanced usage of database system and also get to know the basics to work with XML.</p>

<h2 id="the-summary-of-material">The Summary of Material</h2>

<p>You might checkout <a href="https://github.com/yangchenyun/dbclass-exercises">all the exercise code</a> I’ve written for the course and some mindmaps I summarized for the reviews: <a href="/images/assertions-triggers.png">assertions and triggers</a>, <a href="/images/constrains.png">constrains</a>, <a href="/images/transactions.png">transactions</a>, <a href="/images/xml-query.png">XML</a>.</p>

<p>Besides following the class instruction, I added some materials for learning and set up a more convenient development environment. The great learning experience is certainly brought by these improvements which I would like to share.</p>

<h2 id="how-i-approach-the-course-differently">How I Approach the Course Differently</h2>
<p>I have approached the course differently in three aspects:</p>

<ul>
  <li>I read all related chapters in text book.</li>
  <li>I studied and wrote real-world examples.</li>
  <li>I made deliberate effort to setup development environment to ease practice and test.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="more-reading-and-practice">More Reading and Practice</h3>
<p>I followed the text book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Database-Systems-Complete-Edition-ebook/dp/B004XJIVIC/ref=sr_1_2">The Database System - The Complete Book</a> along the course schedule. This is the text book used in former Stanford database courses and it is what the course’s material origined. I read related chapters in the text book after watching the videos. Reading would reveal some points I’ve missed in the video and help build up a systemetic view over the topic.</p>

<p>As I work as a programmer, I applied the knowledge I learned in this course directly to several relational database based projects. </p>

<p>I wrote a lot of <a href="https://gist.github.com/yangchenyun/5254141">raw SQLs</a> to fetch analytic data against our production database, it helped me to understand subqueries, natural joins and aggregations in the real world.  </p>

<p>I substituted the backend with <code>sqlite</code> for <a href="https://github.com/yangchenyun/ask/compare/cf510240b0f6f1b52d69426c4ba38227c0de2efc...master">one command line tool</a> I was building at local hackthon.</p>

<p>To understand the advanced usage of triggers and constrains, I also read the source code of <a href="https://github.com/SquareSquash/web/blob/master/db/migrate/1_initial_schema.rb">squash</a>, an open source tool we use internally for bug tracking.</p>

<h3 id="tune-the-tools">Tune the Tools</h3>

<p>Another improvment I made is the development environment. I wanted to make it as easy and quick as possible to test out codes. This is the principal rule I’ve learned from former programming experience. Thus I made some deliberate effort to tune up the development environment.</p>

<p>As my major editor is <code>vim</code>, I use the database plugin <a href="http://www.vim.org/scripts/script.php?script_id=356"><code>dbext</code></a> to play with SQL. <code>dbext</code> enables me to execute SQLs and get the result back in my editor. Instead of editing the SQL, doing copy-and-paste, printing the result out, I could write, run, edit, run, cleanup, run with one simple key binding. This convenience was very helpful when solving complex problems. I could start with some instinct ideas and tested them out right away and improved based on the result I got back. This fast cycle of feedback s helped to evolve one idea to one correct solution.</p>

<p><img src="/images/dbext-img.png" alt="dbext image" /></p>

<p>Later, when I was working with XQuery, I missed the convenience I got from <code>dbext</code>. So I decided to implement it myself. Together with some <a href="https://github.com/yangchenyun/dbclass-exercises/tree/master/utils/bin">bash script</a> and a <a href="https://github.com/yangchenyun/dbclass-exercises/blob/master/utils/xquery-helper.vim">vim function</a>, I built the same experience for XQuery editing. One key binding would fire the XQuery expression against the xml file and return the result right in the editor.</p>

<p><img src="/images/xquery-img.png" alt="xquery image" /></p>

<p>There is also simple <a href="https://github.com/yangchenyun/dbclass-exercises/tree/master/utils/bin">bash script</a> to make working with relational algebra compiler <code>ra</code> and xslt compiler easier.</p>

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s next?</h2>
<p>The <a href="https://class2go.stanford.edu/db/Winter2013/pages/extra-problems">extra problems</a> included in the DBClass is well designed and is aimed to test more practical skills. I will finish them within this week.</p>

<p>DBclass has covered a wide range of topics in such a short period, but it also omits some concepts such as schemes, procedures, functions which are also widely used in modern databases. I will refer to the book and database system documentations to fill the gap.</p>

<p>Thanks for all the class2go team and Professor Jennifer Widom to carry out such an excellent course.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
